is
Carl hello welcome back
everyone I'm here with Alex
aoria we may have Carl join we may have
someone else join if you want to join
maybe write it in the YouTube live chat
and maybe I'll email you a link
otherwise write some
questions however to kick things off
Alex feel free to say hello and start in
and I know that there's things that we
can explore together sure you just
picked it back to me and I was saying to
you all right well I I'll just introduce
myself because I'm not entirely sure how
most of the audience if they know of who
I am so I'm Alex Ria I am a
computational neuroscientist and
cognitive scientist who has worked for
active inactive inference and
specifically predictive coding versions
of it for quite some time I'm Carl's
friend and collaborator uh some of you
might be aware of more of our recent
arguments of mortal computation which is
a Cory or a new coraly or another coraly
of the free energy principle and uh yeah
and you know I'm all about what's wrong
with deep learning in machine
intelligence and I'm usually the guy you
go to if you want to attack back
propagation of Errors large language
models Transformers kind of relates to a
lot of the discussion I was able to
catch Snippets of earlier today so if
you want me to help dismantle what's
what's the problem with deep
learning you know that that can be fun
too so that at least if nothing else
everyone now knows who I am Carl needs
no
introduction maybe start off with that
while I try to figure out why he cannot
join oh okay uh what part of that do you
want me
to I mean I can go into Manifesto but
I'm not sure that's what this panel
should be about
out maybe beginning with a five minute
Manifesto and then there will be some
questions and uh we'll see where we
get well maybe to try to make it useful
to the audience uh for the moment
although I wasn't intending the panel to
be focused about that um maybe one thing
that we can talk about is there was this
discussion during the active inference
Workshop about metabolism and sort of
instill a homeostatic metabolic drive a
survival almost orientation to machine
intelligence and so uh Carl and I have
now been arguing for probably now about
more than a year since uh our paper came
out like on yeah around November
actually start of November talking about
uh another way to redesign reformulate
to use Ma's earlier uh uh wording uh
intelligence itself uh particularly
machine intelligence
and so mortal computation without again
if for those that might not be familiar
actually my friend Jeff also like two
years ago introduced this phrase the
idea that computation or intelligent
calculations and substrate uh in
biological natural systems are entangled
and it's very hard to divorce those two
concepts uh whereas computer science and
a lot of like what cat GPT is or large
language models or your favorite
GPT structure is Immortal which is the
idea that we can copy that program
including its weight tensors and it's
encoded knowledge and place it on GPU
server you want and it'll behave roughly
the same there's nothing inherent about
its physical
instantiation uh in this universe uh
that dictates or shapes or uh
necessarily embodies it right and so
there's this like move to uh embodiment
by the way active in the free energy
principle has all of these
characteristics mortal computation which
is again as the concept I explain
earlier Carl and I sort of uh recast it
we strongly redid it and said that um uh
because while Jeff didn't want to
necessarily directly explore it we put
it as it's just basically thinking of
the free energy principle and taking it
to its natural extreme conclusion which
is that machine intelligence systems uh
because they are inherently bound to
their substrate must focus on this
survival objective right and the free
energy principle and one of its ways to
talk about it uh basically is saying you
know we have a markup blanket or a
nested system of marup blankets and our
goal in this universe is to protect
those internal States uh yet interact
vicariously with our external States and
so that eventually gives us our ultimate
goal which is to prevent ourselves from
disintegration into a heat bath it's a
very physics uh form of thinking about
identity and identity construction um
but this is kind of what's centrally
missing in basically all of machine
intelligence um is this the completely
right path to go there's plenty of
criticisms and I'm not one to say that
there's only one direction we need to go
if we ever want something like
artificial general intelligence um but
this might be a path worth exploring it
also addresses the Energy Efficiency
arguments I was hearing earlier
discussed uh Transformers particular l
in large language models are uh grossly
negligent of their energy costs they
often times have the carbon footprint of
a large city and that's actually now out
of date as you know Carl and I wrote
that about a year ago um there's even
discussions I find kind of humorous by
individuals I'm not going to
particularly name saying we should be
powering now uh these Transformers and
large language models with nuclear power
plants and so we're kind of going down
the rabbit hole of let's just burn as
much of our resources as we can to just
get this particular type of
intelligence I argue very strongly
narrow AI uh and we're cheating
ourselves of looking and embracing
actually Energy Efficiency uh which
would lead us towards the real grand
goal of green AI uh because clal GL
global climate change is clearly and
empirically a thing and we should be a
little worried about that so uh mortal
computation sort of helps steer
everything into sort of what I would
argue hopefully maybe in multiple years
time the emergence of a whole new field
because I consider at least my personal
take I'd love to have you know heard
Carl wherever he might be um but I
Envision actually mortal computation is
not just like the framework and
definitions that Carl and I talked about
which kind of take free energy uh and
active inference to the strongest
conclusion to a naturalistic machine
intelligence maybe perhaps a new domain
of thought of biomedic intelligence and
where everyone else can come together
and play in this really interesting
space and there's a lot to unpack there
but I don't think we want to make this
about that uh there's plenty of talks
I've given including active inference
Institute we've had a podcast actually I
think it was right when the paper came
out so for those that are interested I
just recommend you to go to the YouTube
channel and watch wonderful videos that
Dan LED
oh is there is there a new link okay
sure was was I just blabbing there to no
one no that was perfect we we we just
hot
swapped okay I was trying to buy
Carl welcome Carl we talking about
you
okay thank you for the overview on
Mortal computation and and and it was a
highlight of the
year um Carl with the evening Sunset
now how um goes it
wait I don't hear you oh oh continue
sorry it's all good Carl
continue can you hear me now yep
excellent yeah I'm sorry about that I
got locked out I was
uh paying the price for enjoying myself
for the first two
hours right I'll
wait just I really enjoyed the um the
intervening sessions um and look forward
to of comenting some the cross cutting
scen yes okay um Alex
mute it's a little noisier on jitsy and
then uh corl um also a little quiet but
we hear you so um what were
the what were the themes that that uh
connected the
presentations that you were in or
otherwise one thing that um struck me
can you hear me all right now is this y
excellent I mean there are lots of lots
of little uh golden nuggets um
throughout all the presentations um but
one um one crosscutting theme was this
notion of community that emerged in
various guises such as the notion of
Commons that was the subject of uh a lot
of the exchanges in the first um in the
first
um uh
presentation um and then the notion of
community that was a Dumont of the the
workshop um and then the not of
coherence and synchronization and
narrative social um science accounts of
that and how that might be formalized in
terms of um joint free energy
minimization ensembles of Agents you
know finding a coherent communal um and
empowered free energy Minima so you know
I thought I I thought that that was a
common theme sort of
focusing much less upon um
individual agents but what happens when
you have a an ecosystem of Agents um and
what
principles um can be brought to the
table to understand interactions or
ensembles of Agents so I I have a number
of you know lots of things came to mind
I was trying as a physicist to sort of
um rewrite all of these wonderful
Concepts um in a mathematical way or or
a physics way um so for examp examp I
was think about the importance of
Commons and it struck me that one way
that we could motivate the choice of
capital c for prior preferences uh would
be that these are the common goals and
the and the C characteristics States um
that are shared between um multiple
agents uh and of course um the last
presentation took us through some of the
mechanisms and the capital c circular
capital c
causality um that leads to this Capital
C coherence so you know which originally
was meant to be constraints in the sense
of a constraint Maxim entry principle um
or cost in the you in a reinforcement
learning uh reinforcement learning
setting but coming back of course all
this started when I was hearing about
Commons and how it underwrote
communities it it is very interesting
how development and the presentations
have
proceeded a lot more about the
communication and somewhat of the
multi-agent coordination as opposed to a
longer memory train for individuals or
deeper prospection for one individual
um and in a way the
renormalization method brought a a
Clarity or a rigor to what had already
been qualitatively
explored from 2013 and Life as We Know
It And all these other works that we're
talking about multiscale systems and
about blankets of blankets and within
this year to make it timely we start to
see some of the
ways in which that compositionality can
actually be brought into the generative
models that we've seen I mean it looks
like the textbook figure 4.3 and the
nested models and now that's
actually the
motif that gives a way of looking at a
multiplicity at the more inactive level
as having a Unity at a higher level
Alex in
your designing or work how how does the
single agent or
multi-agent design come into
play
now yeah yeah can hear okay good yeah I
was having mic troubles earlier um well
so it's kind of interesting I think I've
spent most of my career at the agent
level in the sense that I want to build
I don't think we have right the single
agent and I and I think it's kind of
important to sort of scope that out from
an architectural learning perspective
I'm very much a fan of like Carl's
arguments and you know I Echo them
myself a lot which is the idea of the
inference learning and structural time
scales uh I still think we have a lot to
do but if I were to say how in my
research the multi-agent approach really
comes into play well I do think a lot in
terms of assemblies or ensembles right
putting together multiple circuits I'm a
I'm a huge proponent of another type of
this comes from cognitive science called
the common model of cognition uh I'm not
sure how many in the audience are
familiar with it but it's sort of like a
generic reprint that has emerged over
the last several decades of cognitive
science to say that we can think about
and take our current Knowledge from
neurop physiology and cognitive studies
that brain has these rough levels of
organization different types of memory
we have the motor cortex we have phas of
gangway we have all these very important
structures and we can start appending to
them some
functionality and so in that sense
that's where I think of multiple agents
right because you can start breaking
apart using again Carl and I've have
argued this the mean field approximation
uh there's natural mean field
approximations that emerg through the
result of ution where you have these
little substructures that communicate
with each other um obviously the sparse
connectivity that Carl mentioned and his
talk this morning is uh kind of
indicative of how these little
substructures emerge and then
communicate and perform sort of like
what uh Marvin Minsky would have said
you know sort of a society of mind right
uh so it's kind of a call back to that
and I think in that regard I often uh
one branch of my work often tries to
highlight and emphasize bring forth that
notion of cognitive Blueprinting or
cognitive structure um because then we
can start filling in the pieces with
what we know about
neurobiology like for example I use
predictive coding quite a bit uh you
know to fill in those gaps and so I
think in that sense I think a lot of
interacting subsystems you could think
of those as agents and then my final
comment uh without letting myself blab
too much uh I have worked in
neuroevolution so there is another scale
Above This which is you know you do need
to account for how multiple mortal
computers or multiple agents interact
with each other um and so I think in
that regard I have done some work with
very simplified agents where you can
kind of abstract away the neuroscience
and just say I want to look at these
little tiny systems that interact and
then we can you know modify them through
genetic algorithms and neuroevolution so
there is a little bit of that like
higher level uh societal kind of
learning I have looked at that and I
think a big challenge just to bring it
to the audience for the panel is uh
merging those time scales in a in a
coherent and efficient way I still think
well there has been good work I know
Daniel you work on and Colony
optimization as well and other types of
kind of aggregate algorithms uh I think
bringing those time scales together and
really interacting with what we
currently know about single agents even
like the common model of cognition and
going back to the highest level which is
this multi-agent evolutionary time scale
is a Grand Challenge and how do we of
course effectively simulate those in a
way that anyone can play with this I
think is a big Challenge and yeah and I
think I'll kind of stop there before I
go down more
radicals neuroevolution and neural
Darwinism something Carl and and others
have also explored it's like they're all
and then the multiple nested time scales
multiple nested spatial
scales it's like there's this attractor
to want to come back and find the
unifying
patterns and and it's and how those can
be applied is kind of an exciting
question I'll read one question in the
chat so feel free to give a thought or
take it any direction David Highland
wrote do you view mortal and IM do you
view mortal and Immortal computation as
binary categories or are they more like
two points along a
spectrum actually want Carl to answer
that I mean I could give something but I
really want to hear your thoughts on
that it's your favorite subject though
design I know but I'm actually really
curious if you think of it as a spect
because remember the conversation we've
had with Mike Levan and Chris fields and
we've been sort of debating you know how
important it is to lean into mortality
versus immortality do you think that
there could possibly be anything in
between because I honestly am you know I
think of it kind of more rigidly I'll
just give my aners that and I firmly
think we need to like focus on Mortal
computation but do you think that
they're can be a hybrid in between so
sorry to turn it on you but I'm very
curious to know your thoughts um my my
instinctual answer is no
um having said that I am sure that you
can present some um description of
mortal computation in terms of immortal
algorithms I mean I'm just thinking back
to sort of um um the trilogy due to
David Mah uh but does that mean that
these kinds of descriptions are apt um
for simulating reproducing
understanding um or describing the
actual process I I I suspect not they
may at one level of description they may
be but when it comes to
um applying the principles usually in
computer simulations I suspect that that
just would not work I
mean because Daniel and I were wrestling
with zoom and other um um communication
things I I I may we may have missed
whether you've taken people through the
the the key distinction between Mortal
and Immortal uh computation so Al do you
just want to briefly rehearse the sort
of the two Cardinal views of the of the
distinction um between Mortal and
Immortal uh computation I did I just
wasn't sure if anyone heard me so I
wasn't sure what was going on
Zoom yeah I mean certainly from the
point of view the free energy principle
the free energy principle is a
description of a random dynamical system
um
and as such um it is
um a system that constitutes the world
the you know the lived World um perhaps
not the lived world but certainly a
mortal world um that has um
characteristic time scales and therefore
um the free energy principle and
everything that ensues from that
including active inference um rests upon
that primary assumption that you are
describing a process a mortal process a
a a a process that could have um a
physics um although
um the actual free energy principle
itself is almost pref physics so you
have to derive basic mechanics and
classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics from um the existence the your
the the the mortality of this process
cast in terms of your time involving
systems so in that sense um you know
there is no such thing as Immortal
computation
but I also I don't know if you said it
out loud but I also liked your um more
playful take on Mortal versus Immortal
that if so if software was
Immortal uh and it had some autopoetic
aspect to it then it wouldn't care about
dying so there would be no wait there'
be no way there' be no incentive to have
characteristic States coming back to
another big sea um uh so you know in
that sense they cannot be immortal
computation simply because that is
removing the definitional uh stipulative
definitional aspect of the
characteristic states that we are trying
to describe through the feny principle
and active inference and specific um VAR
variance of that such as predictive
coding but I just pick up on this
crosscutting CC theme uh you also um um
celebrated that with common cognitive
models so again with we've got this this
s notion commonality and um and you
asked the question you how How would how
would one um apply these Notions and if
you like sort of naturalize the common
cognitive model under um a less
anthropomorphic or functionalist active
inference account and you gave the
answer implicit in your question which
how would you simulate these things um I
think Daniel asked the same the same
question indeed the the whole point of
this Symposium is about applications so
I I just wanted to put a question to the
two of you I was um impressed with the
very um clear distinction between
agent-based modeling and the common
cognitive equivalent the where the
agents the members of The Ensemble were
actually for example active inference
agents that seems to me a very big move
and a very difficult thing to actually
do um most of the literature I know in
this area um has at most taken baby
steps into having
ensembles of two agents with authentic
agency in the sense that they can plan
so I'm now limiting um the notion of an
agent Beyond a thermostat or a virus to
those kinds of systems that um have in
mind or part of their Gena model the
consequences of their Lear actions so
they can be future pointing and they can
plan and select from alternative
policies uh and of course the numerics
and the you know the the Practical
difficulties of actually
simulating doing agent-based modeling
for example um with authentic agents in
the mix in the ecosystem um I think is
you know um is a really important
Challenge and a really important
distinction between classical
agent-based models where you put lots of
ther stats or rents tractors together
and see what happens and of course they
have a synchronization manifold and you
can certainly wax lyrical about um
generalized synchrony and and and Joint
free energy minimization of a generic
sort but I think that misses the point I
think Ma was making um
um that you know part of the the
multiple L Loops of circular causality
in sort of your know cultural Niche
construction for example um you know
really does rest upon um the capacity of
any individual within an ensemble um to
um act given they have selected a
particular course of action particular
path into the future which they have
beliefs about the consequences of and
you know to me that that that that is an
authentic kind of agent so you know mean
perhaps well both of you d mean your
your your ethology background um are you
aware of anybody's actually sort of
Bitten the bullet that was introduced to
US during the workshop and actually
started creating active inference agents
that actually plan and learn from each
other and carve out their own Wallington
Landscapes you know finding those sort
of joint joint
Minima I don't know specific uh citation
but certainly you've given a research
Direction and it reminded me of in the
shared protentions work where thinking
about what what does a shared Ensemble
what would it be for a planning Ensemble
or for a collective it could be a shared
protention as in there's the same plan
disseminated across the ant nestmates it
could be that they have different maybe
nonoverlapping but complimentary parts
that would be shared it could be having
a shared reference but they could have
different plans or it could even be a
shared consequence without even a shared
reference so there's so many ways in
which especially when we consider
ensembles that that are
heterogenous and they have different
kinds of umelt different kinds of ways
of engaging with the niche and and
possibly some comment
niche as well as some uniquely
accessible components there's so many
flavors of
Ensemble that I I can can only
hopelessly or helpfully try to think
about what tools and infrastructure and
coordination would even give us a grasp
to be able to sweep or design or
visualize across that otherwise we might
be locked in
way too early to what it means for The
Ensemble to have a collective protention
and then that's not going to apply to
every ant species and if it can't even
apply to all the ants out there then
it's not going to work for
aliens Alex can I can I just respond to
that and then ask ask for your your view
on that one so I think it's a really
important point and um one of the big
takeaways for me on our paper on the
variational synthesis you you're
applying the renormalization group to
the the coupling of evolutionary to um
sort of phenotypic uh time scales was
that it was not uh feasible or
appropriate to talk about consp
specifics in isolation that it was you
had to have the all the varieties of
predators and praise and things that we
um that not even animate not even agents
in the mix to actually
um derive the um your the
non-equilibrium steady States at
particular at particular scales which
you know speaks directly it is not um it
is not uh useful to um you know if you
like take the idealized gas mentality of
20th century physics and now apply it to
agent-based modeling to assume that all
the agents are exchangeable and are
identical in some s sense and then are
converging on some common narrative um
or some common um uh is not the right
way to you know to simulate these things
you can't do Predator prey relationships
you know for example you can't have um
even simple economic games uh but
furthermore you you you when people talk
about depletion of resources you
actually have to model the resource you
know whether it's oxygen food or water
as things in in that ecosystem so I
think that's a really important
observation which just speaks to the
challenge of using numerical studies to
test out some of the hypotheses that uh
that we' you know being being exposed to
um you
know you know if one just pursues
agent-based modeling without introducing
that heterogeneity I think one is making
exactly the same mistake um that people
make when they apply uh equilibrium
physics to non-equilibrium systems um
you know you know
a true gas is not an ideal gas and it
only has the kinds of properties and
breaks detailed balance and expresses
non-ra in virtue of the fact that there
is no exchangeability you can't assume
that every atom or every agent in our
context um is exchangeable with with
every other
agent and to connect again to Commons
and and that model of well within the
firm we assume Co cooperativity and
hierarchy in the market we have a
flatness and a competitiveness and then
there's this Commons that has sort of
elements of each so then I think about
doing ecosystem modeling it'd be like
well we have within the ant colony we
assume cooperativity possibly hierarchy
among ant colonies you have red and
tooth and Claw and
competition and then it's like but can
there be a unifying
framework that would have the two
genotypes and two phenotypes and two
species and two adjacent niches and keep
on adding in these levels of Distinction
and seeing all those different variables
in their joint Evolution across multiple
time scales rather than the
concatenation of a Cooperative
hierarchical game NE Within in a lateral
competitive game it's like capturing
what those models get the the width and
the height of but bringing it
into a framework where it's being seen
as just one joint evolving
process so C is the letter of the
day uh Alex can you speak to CES of
cells
what what that kind of heterogeneity and
structured diversity would look like
from a point of view of tissue for
example or an organ okay wait what was
the c word you said I just didn't hear
it it's any any word starting with a
letter C you can use but you have to oh
I have to use okay this is the
game um Community I'm gonna pick that
one just because it starts with c um so
okay Carl threw in organs and organel
but I'm going to push that aside for
just a minute to address I think one of
the questions I heard emerge from yours
and Carl's discussion which was uh is
there anything like what you are arguing
for which is avoiding the mistakes and
by the way Predator prey model came
immediately to your speaking Carl um
about these classical models that
assumed interchangeable agents and is
there anything that looks at these
heterogenous systems or heterogenous
agent interactions and a couple of
thoughts I don't think there's anything
like directly what we would want and I
think that ties or centers around our
even the arguments you and I and many
others in the community are making about
uh why it's difficult to show case why
active inference is so important even
for places like machine intelligence um
but I did write some thoughts quickly uh
so I do think uh the first thing that
came to mind weirdly enough was an
application in the world of machine
intelligence where they had some
environment where they had a community
of even though I say it with slight
distaste large language models or Chad
gpts or gpts that had some extra
modality equipped to them and they had
this like little Community now it was a
virtual very simplified Niche if you
will um but the idea is that they could
observe this community um and so these
different gpts would and I can try to
dig up the paper and send it to Daniel
later it's one of my students that
actually pointed it out to me they would
different roles they had different
personalities if you will um and I know
that they investigated that to some
degree now of course that doesn't have
any active inference in there and I'm
not sure what degree of maybe perhaps
light reinforcement learning being
introduced but there is something like
that and there is slight baby steps if
you will uh in investigating some notion
of embodi multi-mod and agent systems I
think the AI Community is
still sort of barely starting to embrace
embodiment let alone enactivism and let
alone embeddedness which is the idea of
a community to go back to the seword of
multiple agents interacting with each
other um and investigating how do social
norms and merge or cultural norms and
cultural constraints and relationships
at this like more Global level so I
think there is a little bit of those
Sparks of that thought and obviously I
might not be aware of further follow-ups
another place that uh I at least see the
potential of no longer having these
interchangeable particle like agents is
in multi-agent robotics um I know that
they have done things like soccer
competitions and they have these little
and again each of those robots they are
the embodiment of what you and I want
which is a version of a mortal computer
so it's a little like assembly of mortal
computers and there's a Cooperative
nature so and then a competitive nature
so you get a little bit of a very
constrained real physical real world
Niche um obviously it's in the
constraints of it's a soccer game or
some very simple task so I know in
multi-agent robotics there is some
development along this path and it'd be
wonderful to have like a a a hardcore
because I'm more of a simulation
roboticist a hardcore roboticist to talk
to us about the state of multi-agent
Robotics I think that's the place where
you could begin to test uh hypotheses
and kind of or theories that are
constructed even from active inference
point of view uh into these real world
robotic multi- assemblies you know they
have like we could analyze the
competition Cooperative Dynamics I think
that's our best bet in terms of what
maybe exists at the closest to literal
agents that aren't just very simplified
even though they make simplifications in
robotics too uh in order to have a
little brain in there that you know does
something meaningful usually learning is
turned off which is my own criticism of
Robotics um and I think the last comment
I wanted to make and again getting back
to the Notions of what we need so again
you and I have a fondness I think for
some of cybernetics and cybernetics has
this notion of complex emergent systems
and we you know you have these little uh
building blocks at one level that follow
their own physics or their own physical
laws and then they maybe assemble or
emerge into these higher level building
blocks that are subject to their own
laws then you have bottom up in top down
causation which is a notion that you
know comes from cybernetics and we
always talk about that but then I think
about like Santa you you might be
familiar with the Santa Fe Institute and
all their wonderful work like uh what
was it not just Herbert Simon but uh uh
John Holland and all the wonderful work
on complex adaptive systems but they
always did at the end of the day when
they simulated it they did the particle
thing this interchangeable particle
simulation and then tried to analyze
like those convergence properties
or those emergent rhythms or patterns
that kind of emerge in those systems
with no to my knowledge and you know and
I did study complex adaptive systems a
while ago uh not with that heterogenity
and let alone any of the complex agents
that we could begin to design today even
with deep learning regardless of its
limitations and so I think that that
maybe even turns into an answer to your
question highlights an open opportunity
Maybe revisiting and recasting Notions
of cybernetics and complex adaptive
systems in this idea of well can we
actually build more complex agents uh
for example that actually have neural
substrate structures or something that
we can simulate and then learn to
acquire their own characteristics in
their Niche I think the reason that
maybe a lot of people avoid it or maybe
why I don't perceive uh development in
that direction is the problem also of
Niche and you and I also had an and a
not to try to highlight this paper but
in the appendix we talked about the body
Niche problem uh and that is this issue
that uh you need a niche if you don't
have a niche and you're designing these
agents independently like deep learning
typically does to apply to any Niche uh
you're missing really half the problem
which is understanding the physical laws
and how do we simulate them such that
people can then play with those models
maybe you don't have access to a xenobot
like Michael Levan does or I don't have
access to organizes though I wish I did
um but you know maybe we can simulate
these and so I think that we need the
community may this is a call to the
community to develop uh viable niches
virtual morphologies virtual uh areas
that we can then connect these agents
and then simulate many of them and try
to analyze and understand do the things
we predict even with these
interchangeable particle models apply to
these heterogenous communities that
might emerge and again I guess that just
to wrap up and I promise I'm done you
brought up organel and organs and I
think that highlights something that I
wish I had more easy access to rather
than uh being put into this position
where I well may I need to build it
which is you know these virtual organ
systems or virtual organ organel and
trying to understand how these dynamical
systems interact and then I can kind of
take that as that's my body or that's
where my Mark and I can kind of start to
put some instantiation of blankets and
then say Okay I want to instill maybe a
neural circuit maybe I put in a
predictive coding model into this kind
of virtual morphology so I can analyze
and understand does do these
interactions of the time scills actually
come through when we actually build you
know physical instantiations of these
models and so I think that's going to be
one of the biggest roadblocks to even my
dreams of mortal computation which is
this notion of myology something that we
can actually work with that it gets as
close as we can to reality without
reality and in Niche um because once you
have those problems solved then you can
start building multi and if you have
efficient way to simulate them and I'm
sure lots of people that are watching
might be worried uh because it's very
hard to simulate you know real physical
systems let alone allow machine
intelligence researchers to play with
them so I blabbed a little bit there but
does that sort of give you some
something to bite on based on your
questions something to chew on something
to consider um in the last little bit
I'll I'll ask some questions so I'm
going to read one from the live chat and
then anyone else we'll just do some
quick fun random questions sort of like
sampling from the uncertainties
expressed uncertainties of our live chat
colleagues okay Pablo FM wrote is
playing a simulation acquiring knowledge
SL experiences through simulation of
scenarios
and how can we use active inference to
do
games how do you fellows make your
active inference work playful and fun if
or
when let you go Carl you go I'm not sure
if there are two there there are two
questions there
um a practical answer to um why you
might want to
instantiate um a simulation environment
with active inference agents or indeed
just a single agent in the in the spirit
of computational phenotyping but I think
probably more interesting in the um in
the context of um communities of Agents
um is in the spirit of this sort of
cognitive um agent based modeling um is
the ability to um parameterize the
priors of the agents to best explain or
replicate Legacy data from a particular
ecosystem be it Financial
epidemiological
meteorological
um purely ethological
um and having optimized the parameters
you then roll out into the future
and in rolling out into the future you
now have the opportunity to have a
grounded in principle base optimal plus
inactiv ISM and embedded um um estimate
of what is likely to happen in the
future again in the spirit of weather
forecasting but of course this becomes
much more um if like useful um when you
have control of the system so Financial
Market forecasting or epidemiological
forecasting or uh climate change
forecasting
you assuming that there's a substantive
um an um anthropomorphic um um
anthropological um contribution to
um climate and you all the other factors
that uh you know um pertain to um
resilience and uh resistance to things
he you know health and the like um as
soon as you can
intervene then once you've got a digital
twin of this ecosystem that has been
optimized in relation to um the past
data in the sense that this now has the
highest model evidence or marginal
likelihood in relation to that Legacy
data you've then got an opportunity to
do scenario modeling with interventions
so you can now ask questions what would
happen if we um cut this Supply CH train
chain what would happen if we impose
this lockdown in this viral pandemic
what would happen and so on and so forth
furthermore because you've got um um
uncertainty in the mix because this is
effectively going to be um you're using
variation procedures that we use in
active inference to actually simulate um
the behavior that best matches the um
the Legacy data you've also got for free
uncertainty quantifications and not only
can you say if I interv on this system
and did this um then we would uh I can
predict that in six months time or in
six years time that and I can give you
Bas in credibil intervals o over that
moreover you can now apply the
principles of active inference to roll
out under different interventions which
now become policies and evaluate the
expected free energy of each policy and
select the one under the constraints the
Comm the characteristic outcomes U that
you um commit to at this point in time
and you can now use this scheme to make
recommendations on the basis of the um
the relative probability of this
sequence of interventions versus that
sequence of interventions so I think
there are great practical importances of
being able to put these principles in
silico and basically do Evolution very
very quickly so that tomorrow you can
read the you can read the consequences
probabilistically uh of evolution in
this setting and that setting where the
setting is actually something that we
can intervene on or even if we can't
just to know the consequences of our
Collective Behavior Uh today so I think
that would be um that's why you might
want to make you know to invest in in
these applications um with the fun and
uh having uh and play I think that's a
different issue I think that's basically
um um
one way of looking at the um the way
that authentic agents behave under under
the free energy principle which is
basically to explore and gather the
right kind of evidence that uh provides
literally evidence for their generative
models of of their world um which
basically entails novelty seeking but
now complement this with this um basing
reduction we've been talking about also
trying to find the minimal explanation
for the data and the evidence that has
been secured by exploratory playful
Behavior arriving at particular insights
which uh those are har moments that say
oh I see it's just one of those or this
one thing explains all of this playfully
AC acquired data and perhaps that kind
of mechanism you know may be a really
important aspect of the communal um um
you cognitive agent based or yeah
cognitive agent based I can't quite
remember the acronym it was very nicely
laid out in one of the I have to go back
and look at the live
stream a follow-up question from the
live chat Arno wrote I agree with the
approach to calibrate to pass data and
forecast but it's already quite
challenging for current models that only
have a few parameters to be calibrated
how then does one calibrate prior
beliefs of millions of
Agents I'm talking about epidemiology
and economic models sorry I'm going to
give a technical answer before Alex
gives a gives aedy answer uh you do it
it's only difficult because 99% of
agent-based modeling uh uses the sample
distribution um you do not do that you
use variational you actually um simulate
and roll out the um the um probability
distributions themselves using
variational calculus and that means that
what was yesterday um really difficult
agent-based modeling and certainly
epidemiological modeling now becomes
really trivial uh orders of magnitude
more uh more efficient what you have to
take care of is exactly the thing that
Daniel was was highlighting before which
is a heterogeneity you need to put that
into the mix and this manifests in a
number of ways um so when you apply um
variational procedures to effectively um
roll out population density uh
probability density distributions over
various states of being am I infected am
I staying at home um have I died um you
have to make sure that the heterogeneity
is part of the generative model so this
is sometimes called stratification so
for example in epidemiological models
you'd have eight bands for different age
groups and if you notice the way that
the epidemiological data was generated
was usually age segregated so that
people could stratify their models um
another um way in which this
heterogeneity becomes absolutely crucial
um when you come to um agent-based
modeling in the context of
epidemiological or infectious disease
modeling is called over dispersion now
over dispersion is the fact that uh you
get heavy tailed distributions that
inherit from the heterogeneity so you
get this for free once you put
heterogenity into the model but it does
mean um for every if you like subgroup
of um the population you do induce more
parameters but remember the number of
parameters it doesn't really matter it's
the amount of time that you take to
effectively invert your model and if you
try and do that using sampling based
approaches which is currently the the
norm you could take literally weeks to
uh do something um whereas if you use
variational procedures then you could do
that within within minutes so it's a
really important question a very
practical
one yeah to restate direct variational
inference on beliefs about ensembles
themselves being variational belief
inference on agent level semantic
beliefs rather than sample from the
sample what the agents are
sampling yeah
you're you're you're invoking the The
Twist yes how on Earth can you model a
variational density over things that
have variational densities you can do it
under the f p room because the only
observable things about an agent are on
its Markoff blanket and of course they
are not belief structures so there is a
lawful relationship between you can um
if you like simulate cognitive agents
using traditional agent-based uh
approaches but what you have to do is to
amortize or to or to um um basically
work out the um the mapping between the
history of what something sees um and
what it actually does but in principle
you can do it by marginalizing out the
um the beliefs of the agent in principle
I'm not and that's that's why I asked
that's why I'm so intrigued by this
distinction because that will be a
challenge Alex and then Carl just in our
last minutes here what would you say was
a favorite memory or moment in theory
and practice for active inference this
year and then what are you excited about
for next
year um I'll go I'll go first so a
favorite memory of active inference let
me think quickly well I I mean I'm going
to be a little by
just to give a highlight and a shout out
and everyone will get to share in that
memory if you stick around after the
round table is actually some of the
results from one of my PhD students um
via and he's going to give a talk soon
and uh the idea is that uh one of the
things I was proud of is he's been
working in the area of Robotics which I
think is a really good playground uh is
difficult and hard is it to democratize
for everyone to work with robotics I
think it really shows you how far we
need to go and I think that's a good
place to make strong advances an active
inference um and one of my memories is
that I remember him kind of showing me
uh because he's working with partially
observable Markoff decision processes
and how difficult and
unaddressed it is in the field of
working with raw sensory data to try to
construct these continuous models and I
remember him showing me some of his
models rolled out trajectories in the
future and I I'm always kind of in a
fondest in my heart for generative
models and I remember him playing out
sort of these robotic memories of this
robot trying to you know fantasize where
it would want to go to kind of like move
this block or to knock a ball towards a
go so that was one of those moments
where we were really proud because the
idea is we actually we actually made a
breakthrough uh in actually showing that
we can construct a very robust framework
that applied across all these robotic
control problem and so I was immensely
proud of that and so I think my students
drive a lot of some of my fond memories
um and uh and then we got uh Chris
Buckley shout out to him uh to you know
uh kind of give us his insights into our
work too and it was a really really nice
work and so and I think the best way to
say it is stick around if you want to
know how that all works I was really
proud of that so one of my favorite
memories of the
Year awesome Carl with the last words of
a fun memory and
uh a direction or an excitement for next
year right I'm I'm not going to tell you
about my most fun moments that's that's
very personal but my my my my excitement
for next year is to see whether any of
your hairs go gray after you do the
master ceremony of these of not only
these uh Symposium all the meetings
because for those people who don't know
Daniel has to run this almost
singlehandedly nonstop for a marathon
sometimes 10 hours at a time I don't
know how he does it at Le unless you're
using hair dye you're you're you're
standing up physically remarkably well
sir so I just see how long that
lasts thank you Carl I look forward to
the marathon
changing continuing and flourishing in
the coming
year we appreciate you Daniel thank you
guys it's been
awesome okay thanks a lot see you soon
nice talking to you guys bye
everyone
e e